http://youtu.be/LD1dd8uRfj4
http://youtu.be/LD1dd8uRfj4
(JONATHAN VALVANO) Next, let's look at how the components of an embedded
(JONATHAN VALVANO) kế tiếp, hãy xem những thành phần của hệ thống nhúng
system fit together.
kết hợp với nhau như thế nào.
We're going to have the computer.
Ta có cái máy tính.
And we're going to connect through the input output ports.
và ta kết nối với cổng input output.
Some will be just output.
1 số thứ chỉ có output.
Some will be both input and output.
1 số có cả input và output
And some will be just input.
Số khác chỉ có input.
And we're going to connect these up to devices, which we've already listed as
Ta sẽ kết nối vào những thiết bị khác, ở đây ta có
electrical, mechanical, chemical, biological, optical...
điện, cơ, hoá, sinh, quang...
Your list can go on and on.
Bạn có thể kết nối thêm nhiều thiết bị nữa.
Now, let's look at inside the computer.
Giờ nhìn vào trong máy tính.
In the computer, we said it has a processor.
Trong máy tính, ta có 1 vi xử lý.
The processor is the brains, the thing that performs actions.
Vi xử lý là bộ não, thực thi mệnh lệnh.
And we're going to connect up to this processor two types of memory.
Vi xử lý kết nối với 2 loại bộ nhớ.
We have a random access memory, which is volatile.
Ta có bộ nhớ truy xuất ngẫu nhiên, là kiểu bộ nhớ volatile
And it will contain our data.
Nó chứa dữ liệu.
Volatile means if we shut the power off, the information goes away.
Với loại bộ nhớ này thông tin sẽ biến mất khi mất điện.
And then we have another type of memory called read only memory.
1 loại bộ nhớ khác là bộ nhớ chỉ đọc.
And sometimes we're going to call it flash because that's the technology
Còn được gọi là bộ nhớ flash, là tên của công nghệ này.
that was used to build it.
được dùng để làm ra bộ nhớ này.
And it is nonvolatile.
Là kiểu nonvolatile.
And that means the data does not go away.
Khi mất điện dữ liệu vẫn còn trong bộ nhớ.
And this nonvolatility is important in an embedded system.
Kiểu bộ nhớ này rất quan trọng với hệ thống nhúng.
And what we're going to put in ROM memory is our code or our software
Ta sẽ lưu code của software vào bộ nhớ ROM này.
will go in there.
bộ nhớ ROM này.
And as I mentioned before, an important part of an embedded system
Và như tôi nói lúc trước, 1 phần quan trọng của hệ thống nhúng
is input output.
là input output.
And we're going to connect all these together with a bus.
Và ta phải kết nối tất cả những thứ này vào 1 bus.
So these are the components of our embedded system.
Đây là tất cả những cấu phần của hệ thống nhúng.
The picture that we drew on the previous slide was classified as Von
Hình tôi vẽ trong slide trước gọi là
Neumann computer.
máy tính kiểu Von Neumann.
And that is the two types of memory and the I/O all
Có 2 kiểu bộ nhớ vào I/O
existed on the same bus.
gắn vào cùng 1 bus.
So we had the processor, which is the intelligence that performs actions.
Ta có vi xử lý, là thành phần tính toán.
And we had our RAM memory, which contained the data.
có bộ nhớ RAM, là nơi chứa dữ liệu.
And we had our ROM memory, which contains our instructions and our I/O,
Có ROM, chứa chương trình và I/O,
which performs either output or input to the world.
giao tiếp với bên ngoài.
That was a Von Neumann machine.
Đó là máy Von Neumann.
And we can see that all the information is connected
Ta sẽ thấy tất cả thông tin được truyền tải
across the same bus.
thông qua bus.
The Cortex M, the one we're going to do in this class, is classified as a
Cortex M, vi điều khiển được học trong lớp này, được xếp loại
Harvard architecture.
vào kiến trúc Harvard.
And it is different in the following fundamental way.
Nó khác về cơ bản so với máy tính kiểu Von Neumann.
And that is we still have a processor, which executes instructions.
Ta vẫn có vi xử lý, thực thi câu lệnh.
And we still have ROM, which contains those instructions.
Cũng có ROM, chứa chương trình.
And the processor and the ROM are connected by a bus, which allows you
Vi xử lý và ROM kết nối thông qua 1 bus, cho phép bạn
to decode the op code bus.
để dịch mã mã lệnh.
The ICode bus allows the processor to fetch op codes.
ICode bus này cho phép processor lấy mã lệnh.
But this processor has a second bus.
Vi xử lý này còn bus thứ 2.
And on this second bus, which is called a system bus, we see our RAM,
Bus này goi là bus hệ thống, ta thấy RAM,
which contains our data and our I/O devices, which perform either output
chứa dữ liệu và thiết bị ngoại vi,
or input to the real world.
gắn với bus này.
And having a second bus allows you to do two things at once.
Có thêm bus thứ 2 nghĩa là bạn có thể làm 2 thứ 1 lúc.
At the same time that the processor can be fetching an op code, at the
Vi xử lý có thể lấy mã lệnh,
exact same time the processor is writing data to RAM.
đồng thời ghi dữ liệu vào RAM.
And this way the computer will run much faster.
Bằng cách này máy tính chạy nhanh hơn nhiều.
In fact, the processor that we're going to use, the Texas Instruments
Vi xử lý ta đang xài, Texas Instruments
TM4C123, which is a Cortex M4 processor, actually has five or six
TM4C123, với nhân Cortex M4, thực tế có 5 hay 6
buses allowing up to five or six operations to occur simultaneously.
bus, cho phép 5 hay 6 tác vụ diễn ra cùng lúc.